Guide to the Martin Packard papers
Stanford University Libraries.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives.
Martin Packard papers
1946-1990
1975-1985
M0760
Packard, Martin E.
Varian Associates
29 Linear feet (68 boxes: 67 manuscript boxes; 1 record storage box)
In the late 1940s and early 50s, physicist Martin Packard made significant contributions to the emerging field of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) technology at Stanford University. Packard was later employed by Varian Associates, where he became head of the analytical instrumentation department, Corporate Vice President, and finally Assistant to Board Chairman Edward Ginzton. The collection is largely from his time at Varian, consisting of correspondence and memoranda, subject files maintained as Varian’s reference library, and files related to Varian’s corporate history. Packard’s involvement with the Addiction Research Foundation is also chronicled in part.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives. Stanford University Libraries. 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was given by Martin Packard to Stanford University, Special Collections in 1990.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Associated Materials
Stanford also holds the Varian, Inc., Records (SC0889A), Russell and Sigurd Varian Papers (SC0345), and Edward Ginzton Papers (SC0330). An interview with Packard from 1982 is available in the Stuart W. Leslie Oral histories on the Cold War and American Science.
Biographical Note
Martin Everett Packard, born in 1921, received his B.A. in Physics in 1942 from Oregon State University and began working at Westinghouse Research. In the summer of 1945 (following at stint at UC Berkeley Radiation Lab for the Manhattan Project), Packard was introduced to Felix Bloch by his supervisor at Westinghouse, Stanford physics alumnus Daniel Alpert. Bloch explained to Packard his ideas concerning nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), which he termed nuclear induction. The following week Packard enrolled as a graduate student at Stanford University, working with professors Bloch and William Hansen on Stanford’s first NMR experiments. As part of this experiment, Packard was the first to detect the nuclear magnetic resonance of protons in water in January 1946.
Bloch, together with Harvard physicist E. M. Purcell, shared the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1952 for their development of NMR. Aware of its commercial potential, inventor and Stanford alum Russell Varian convinced Bloch to patent NMR, which Russ and his brother Sigurd then licensed. This exclusive license was transferred to Varian Associates when they founded the company in April 1948. The first commercial NMR spectrometer was built by Varian in 1950.
Meanwhile Packard, after earning a PhD in Physics in 1949, remained at Stanford as an instructor. In 1951, with students James Arnold and Srinivas Dharmatti, he discovered how NMR could be applied to organic compounds, opening the field of magnetic resonance analysis in organic chemistry. At the end of the term Packard joined Varian, as had many of Bloch’s former students. Thanks to the license, Varian led the field in NMR commercialization. Packard, along with James Arnold, James N. Shoolery, Emery Rogers, Forrest Nelson, and Wes Anderson, worked with NMR at Varian, “building NMR from a theoretical concept to one of the most widely used tools in analytical chemistry,” as his bio states.
Continuing his research path, Packard published papers, developed with Russell Varian the Proton Free Precession Magnetometer (widely used in geophysics) and is named in eight patents with the company. In 1971 Martin Packard received the IEEE Morris E. Leeds Award "for his pioneering research leading to the practical use of nuclear magnetic resonance for the accurate measurement of magnetic fields, and for his contributions to the spectrometry of complex molecules." Packard retired from Varian in 1989.
Scope and Contents
In the late 1940s and early 50s, physicist Martin Packard made significant contributions to the emerging field of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) technology at Stanford University. NMR involves the measure of electromagnetic radiation absorbed and emitted by nuclei in magnetic fields. NMR is the underlying principle behind MRI and other medical imaging techniques. It also has important applications in chemistry, biology, and geology. Packard was employed by Varian Associates, who, building on their success with the klystron, were market leaders in the commercial application of NMR technology. The collection is from his time at Varian, and therefore should also appeal to those researching that company’s history, or the birth of Silicon Valley.
While Packard came to Varian with NMR expertise, his role in the company quickly expanded, and the files contained here cover many aspects of Varian’s business. There are two main series of Varian correspondence and internal memoranda from the 1960s through the 80s, arranged chronologically. Packard maintained several document files as a sort of reference library, with each document (correspondence, memoranda, and background articles and papers) numbered and indexed. There are files for Varian’s dealings with the People’s Republic of China and the USSR, files on health concerns in radio frequency and microwave technologies (“Biological Effects”), as well as a general subject file arranged alphabetically.
The collection contains a variety of material related to Varian’s corporate history, much of which was assembled for Packard’s “The Varian Story” lecture delivered at the Pittsburgh Conference on Analytical Chemistry in 1980. Most of these files are contemporary remembrances in the form of articles, papers, correspondence, and transcripts. However, there is a set of Russell Varian research notes, papers and patents from the late 1940s and 50s, and photocopies of the Varian newsletter from the late 1940s through the 70s. There is correspondence with Stuart W. Leslie about an unpublished Varian history, essays by W.G. Proctor, Dorothy Varian, and others, and various photographs, some of which are likely original prints. The last files involve Varian Fellows’ efforts to reinvigorate the company in the late 1980s. Historical files also include related information concerning Felix Bloch, NMR, Stanford University, and SLAC. Other Varian files include expense reports, sales brochures for spectroscopes, chromatographs, and other instruments, and records of the Palo Alto Capital Company (Varian’s Minority Enterprise SBIC).
Packard was a member of two National Academy of Science panels on technology transfer and national security, and there is correspondence, memoranda, draft reports, and background information from both panels. He was also president of the Addiction Research Foundation, Avram Goldstein’s research clinic devoted to studying the physiological basis for drug addiction, and there are organizational files through its dissolution in 1989. Of course Packard’s own speeches, papers and other writings are also present, most of which can be found in their own series. There are also many notebooks, planners and business cards, as well as vacuum tubes and other unidentified machine parts.
Access Terms
Addiction Research Foundation (U.S.).; Ginzton, Edward L. (Edward Leonard), 1915-; Goldstein, Avram; Packard, Martin E.; Varian Associates; Nuclear magnetic resonance.; Radiation--Health aspects; Science and industry.; Science--History.; United States--History--Trade relations
Collection Contents
- 1. Varian correspondence, 1962-1986
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Photographs, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    Photographs and correspondence concerning the use of a magnetoscope in an archeological expedition locating Toltec sculpture in San Lorenzo, Mexico.
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Barringer Research Ltd., 1973 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence [USA], 1982 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence [USA], 1983 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence [USA], 1984 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence [USA], 1985 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence [USA], 1986 (Box 52, Folder 2)
- 2. Varian interoffice memoranda
  - Memoranda, 1966-1967 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1968 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda, 1969 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda, 1970 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda, 1971 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda, 1972 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1973 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda, 1974 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda, 1975 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda, 1976 (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda, 1978 (Box 53, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda, 1979 (Box 53, Folder 10)
  - Memoranda, 1980 (Box 53, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda, 1981 (Box 53, Folder 12)
  - Memoranda, 1983 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda, Correspondence, 1985 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda, Correspondence, 1986 (Box 54, Folder 3)
- 3. Varian document files
  Numbered documents for Varian's reference library, with computer printouts of various indexes (i.e. by author, chronologically, etc.). There are numbered documents elsewhere in the collection, without indexes.
  - 3.1 Biological Effects, 1975-1989
    Correspondence, memoranda, and background information (articles, papers, and other publications), in approximately chronological order. In a letter to a cousin in 1983, Packard wrote “one of my jobs is to keep abreast of any potentially harmful biological effects of electrical or magnetic fields," and this file reflects that effort.
    - Indexes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 0001-0020 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 0021-0040 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 0041-0060 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 0061-0080 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 0081-0082 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 0083-0100 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 0101-0120 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 0121-0140 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 0141-0160 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 0161-0180 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 0181-0200 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 0201-0220 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 0221-0240 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 0241-0260 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 0261-0280 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 0281-0300 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 0301-0320 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 0321-0340 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 0341-0360 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 0361-0380 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 0381-0400 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 0401-0420 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 0421-0440 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 0441-0460 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 0461-0480 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 0481-0483 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 0484-0500 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 0501-0503 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 0504-0520 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 0521-0540 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 0541-0560 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 0561-0580 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 0581-0599 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 0601-0620 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 0621-0640 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 0641-0660 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 0661-0680 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - [unnumbered] (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 3.2 PRC [People's Republic of China], 1972-1986
    Correspondence, memoranda, and background information (articles, papers, and other publications), in approximately chronological order. These files chronicle the emergence of normalized trade relations with communist China. Varian activity began around 1972 when Carl Djerassi was involved with hosting a delegation of scientists from the Chinese Academy of Sciences and approached Varian for a tour. In 1977, Varian was in China for a trade fair. By 1986, China was responsible for $10-15 million in sales, Beijing had a sales office and two service centers, and there were manufacturing licenses for six products.
    - Indexes (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 0980-0999 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1000-1019 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1020-1099 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1100-1139 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1140-1199 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1200-1239 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1240-1299 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1300-1339 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 1340-1369 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1370-1399 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1400-1437 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1438-1499 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1500-1569 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1570-1599 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1600-1659 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1660-1699 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1700-1455 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1756-1799 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1800-1869 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1870-1899 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1900-1959 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1960-1999 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 2000-2040 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 2041-2099 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 2100-2145 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 2146-2199 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 2200-2255 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 2256-2299 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 2300-2345 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 2346-2399 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 2400-2439 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 2440-2499 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 2500-2539 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 2540-2599 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 2600-2649 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 2650-2699 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 2760-2799 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - 2700-2759 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - 2800-2899 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - 2900-2922 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - 2923-2944 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - 2945-2999 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - 3000-3049 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - 3050-3059 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - 2100-3149 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - 3150-3199 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - 3200-3214 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - 3215-3252 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - 3253-3299 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - 3.3 USSR, 1973-1986
    Correspondence, memoranda, and background information (articles, papers, and other publications), in approximately chronological order. The file begins with correspondence and reports from Edward Ginzton (who was born in Ukraine) from 1973, as well as Ginzton’s “Some Notes on a Trip to Russia” from 1974. Packard’s first trip was in 1976, and subsequent communication is largely business, scientific and government trip and meeting coordination, notably with licensing agency Licensintorg, and the US-USSR Trade & Economic Council. In early 1980 (around 3300-3364), following the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, U.S. trade embargos extended to the suspension of high technology export licenses, and there is a great deal of correspondence concerning this. The files contain much information about the exchange of scientific knowledge, expertise, and technology with Russia, as well as articles about industrial espionage and spying. Related information can be found in Packard’s National Academy of Science panel files under Series 8.
    - indexes (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - 0700-0799 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - 0900-0999 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - 1000-1029 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - 1030-1099 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - 1100-1199 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - 1200-1299 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - 1300-1359 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - 1360-1399 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - 1400-1459 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - 1460-1499 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - 1500-1539 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - 1540-1599 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - 1600-1629 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - 1630-1699 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - 1700-1799 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - 1800-1859 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - 1860-1899 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - 1900-1959 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - 1960-1999 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - 2000-2079 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - 2080-2099 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 2100-2139 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - 2140-2199 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - 2200-2299 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 2300-2359 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - 2360-2399 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - 2400-2449 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - 2450-2499 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 2500-2549 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - 2550-2599 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - 2600-2639 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - 2640-2699 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - 2700-2746 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - 2747-2799 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 2800-2849 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - 2850-2899 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - 2900-2939 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - 2940-2949 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - 3000-3059 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - 3060-3099 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - 3100-3139 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - 3140-3199 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - 3200-3299 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - 3300-3364 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - 3365-3399 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - 3400-3459 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - 3460-3499 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - 3500-3554 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - 3555-3599 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - 3600-3649 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - 3650-3699 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - 3700-3730 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - 3731-3799 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - 3800-3899 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - 3900-3949 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - 3950-3999 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - 4000-4042 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - 4043-4099 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - 4100-4149 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - 4150-4199 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - 4200-4264 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - 4265-4299 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - 4300-4364 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - 4365-4399 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - 4400-4458 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - 4459-4499 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - 4500-4554 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - 4555-4599 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - 4600-4619 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - 4620-4659 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - 4660-4759 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - A.A. Sokolov, I.M. Ternov. Reliativistskii Elektron (Moscow, 1974). [Inscribed to Packard by Ternov], 1965 (Box 34)
- 4. Varian subject files
  includes numbered "USA Document" files.
  - USA - Document Index (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Activity Reports, 1984-1986 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Archiving (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Artificial Intelligence (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Biotechnology (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Budget, 1984-1986 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Bulow, George (Consultant) (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Cancer (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Cancer Eye Papers (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Carcinogens (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Computer Services (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - CVA Market Research Report, 1973 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Dehmelt, Hans - Correspondence, Reprints, etc. (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Endorphins (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Energy - Transparencies, Related Papers (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - EPR (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Export (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Fluorescent Instrumentation (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Fourier Spectroscopy (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Goldstein, Avram - Reprints [see also Addiction Research Foundation] (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Good RF Practices Committee (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Gordon Research Conference, 1978-08 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Gravimeter (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Gyrotons (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Hoffman - La Roche (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Hyde, Jim - Correspondence, etc. (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Hyperthermia (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - In Vivo NMR 1 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - In Vivo NMR 2 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - In Vivo NMR 3 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - In Vivo NMR 4 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Ion Cyclotron Resonance (ICR) (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Josephson Effects (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Lasers (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Laser Annealing (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Laser Induction Ionization (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - LC/NMR (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Logit (Sylva) (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Magnetometer Project - VACL, 1975-1976 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Magnets (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Mass Spectroscopy, 1967 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Mass Spectroscopy/Gas Chromatography, 1969 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Microfilm, 3 microfilm reel(s) (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Microwave Reprints (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous [unfiled] (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous [unfiled] (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Molecular Computation in Catalytic Copolymer Networks - H.H. Pattee, 1968-1971 (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Multinationals, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - NAS Study [See also Panel on Scientific Communication and National Security] (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - National Bureau of Standards (NBS) (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Neopterin (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Networking (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - NIH Workshops on Technology in Support of Biomedical Research, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - NMR Imaging - Memos, Meetings (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - NMR Imaging - Articles, Preprints, Reprints 1 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - NMR Imaging - Articles, Preprints, Reprints 2 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - NMR Imaging - Talk, 1978-08-23 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - NMR Logging (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - NMR Strategy (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - NMR Study Material, 1981 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - NMR Study - Comments on BAH Presentation by MEP (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Oligonucleotide Machine (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Perseus (R. Weyhrauch) (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Post-Industrial Society, 1971-1973 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Post's Flywheel (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Product Evaluation, 1970 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Productivity (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Program Exchange, TI - PPX-52 Membership (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Research and Development (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Simplex (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Smithsonian Institute (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Superconducting, 1970-1974 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Syva (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Talks (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Thoughts (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Tragedy of the Commons, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Transferred Products, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - UCSF Talk, 1985-10-24 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - UCSF Talk, 1986-10-30 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Universities (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - X-Ray (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - X-Ray Lithography - Synchrotron Radiation (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - X-Ray Microscopy (Box 45, Folder 9)
- 5. Varian history, 1959-1990
  - Varian History - USA Files 1 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Varian History - USA Files 2 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Varian History - USA Files 3 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Varian History- USA Files [unfiled] (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Support For Fellows History [1990] (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Opinion of Fellows [1990] (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - NMR Publication. JTA, WA, JNS, ER, RF (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Varian Oral History Project [1989] (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Photographs - Optical Pumping Apparatus (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Photographs - 1950s (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Photographs - Varian NMR Reception At Stanford, 1983-09 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Photographs - miscellaneous (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Photographs - Varian Story material (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - The Varian Story research material - Varian Newsletter photocopies (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - The Varian Story research material (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - The Varian Story [Martin Packard], 1980 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Talk on Russ and Sig [with research material] (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Russell H. Varian (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Russell Varian Papers - 1950s, 13 folder(s) (Box 48, Folder 5)
    Conclusions on X-13 Grid Cooling -- Consideration of Optimum Design of X-Band Amplifier -- Considerations On Klystron Grids -- Hybrid Velocity Grouped Tubes -- An Idea Utilizing Klystron Type Tubes For Amplification of Signals of Lower Frequency, Such as TV Signals -- Iron Reduction -- Merit of Metals For Klystron Snozzles -- A Method of Geophysical Prospecting -- Novel Radar System for Simultaneously Displaying Doppler and Range Information -- Nuclear Induction Excerpts from Notebook 1946-1951 (2 folders) -- Nuclear Induction Apparatus, Draft of Tech Proposals 1948-1951 -- Paramagnetic Resonance Type of FM System, Patentable Ideas -- Patent Disclosures [most were reviewed in 1964 and contain a note stating "No interest"].
- 6. Varian miscellaneous business files
  - Organizational Charts, 1987-1988 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Planning, 1967-1987 (Box 54, Folder 5)